American Fund for French Wounded Collection
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
American Fund for French Wounded Collection
1915-1918
Ms Coll 56
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
.25
1 box
The American Fund for French Wounded (AFFW), founded in 1915, by American women living abroad, was a women's relief agency to aid wounded soldiers in France in World War I. The materials in this collection originated from the Paris Depot of the organization and include correspondence, circulars, newsletters, and images.
American Fund for French Wounded
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased 2016.
Biographical / Historical
The American Fund for French Wounded (AFFW), founded in 1915, by American women living abroad, was a women's relief agency to aid wounded soldiers in France in World War I. Its American offices were in New York City and there were some 60 chapters in cities in the United States. The organization collected dressings, blankets, pillows, clothing, food, and amusements for French soldiers in French hospitals. These were stored and distributed to hospitals through the Paris Depot. Isabel S. Lathrop was president of the Board of Administration of the Paris Depot and Anna Murray Vail, formerly a botanist and librarian at the New York Botanical Garden, was treasurer and managed the Depot. Dr. Alexis Carrel served as medical advisor. Carrel was in charge of a hospital and laboratory in Compiegne funded by the Rockefeller Foundation for Medical Research in New York. After the war, the mission of the AFFW was continued by the American Committee for Devastated France.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains letters of Anna Murray Vail and Isabel S. Lathrop to Miss Murray Ledyard, a donor in the United States; circular letters written by Anna Vail and other American women in Paris describing visits to hospitals, the devastation in France, the bravery of the soldiers and hospital workers, and the gratitude of recipients for the gifts received; the AFFW's Monthly Report, and Weekly Bulletin, both published in Paris; card photographs of devastated villages and individual buildings in France; postcards; photographs showing the depot and the motor vehicles used for distribution; and miscellany.
Custodial History
This collection appears to have descended from Murray Ledyard Burr of Cazenovia, NY. An issue of AFFW's Monthly Report and a few issues of Weekly Bulletin were added from the Yale University Library.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Charities, Medical -- United States; Medicine, Military; Military hospitals -- France; World War, 1914-1918 -- Hospitals, charities, etc.; World War, 1914-1918 -- Medical care -- France; World War, 1914-1918 -- Personal narratives, American; World War, 1914-1918 -- Women -- United States; Correspondence; Newsletters; Postcards; Photographs; Vail, Anna Murray, 1863-1955; Burr, Murray Ledyard, 1868-1950; Carrel, Alexis, 1873-1944; Carrel, Anne; Lathrop, Isabel S.; Morgan, Ann, Tracy, 1873-1952; Perkins, Elizabeth; Struve, Florence; American Committee for Devastated France; American National Red Cross; War Relief Clearing House For France and Her Allies
- Letters of Anna Murray Vail to Miss Murray Ledyard, 1916-1918 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Typed letters from Anna Murray Vail, at the Paris Depot, to Murray Ledyard, in either Washington, D.C. or Cazenovia, New York. Ledyard was a relative or close friend, since she was addressed as "Dear Murray," and signed with "affection." Vail's letters thank Ledyard for her donations and describe the war and her work in Paris. She discusses the entrance of the U.S. into the war and relations of the A.F.F.W. with the American Red Cross. With the letters is a postcard created for the American Fund for French Wounded showing a woman marking red crosses on supplies and a soldier receiving them. There is also a circular letter dated March 21, 1917. See Folder 6.
- Letters of Isabel S. Lathrop to Miss Murray Ledyard, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Two thank-you letters from the president of the Board of Administration of French office of AFFW.
- Letter of a Belgian soldier to "Mademoiselle", 1917 November 15 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Letter from a Belgian soldier in a hospital thanks the recipient (Murray Ledyard?) for her gift and asks if he might correspond with her.
- AFFW Circular letters, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  The circular letters were written and signed by members of the Paris staff. They were chatty personal accounts of visits to hospitals, describing the conditions on the journey, the staff and patients of the hospital, and the distribution of supplies to soldiers. With these are edited extracts of French letters of gratitude from those assisted by the AFFW. The 1915 folder contains one circular letter dated December 21, 1915 and several pages of extracts.
- AFFW Circular letters, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Folder contains 29 circular letters dating from April 16, 1916 to December 27, 1916, as well as extracts in French of letters of appreciation.
- AFFW Circular letters, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Fifteen circular letters are dated January 1, 1917 to October 27, 1917.
- AFFW Circular letters, undated and incomplete (Box 1, Folder 7)
  An undated letter describes in detail a trip from Paris through Noyon and Chauny and through devastated lands abandoned by the German forces.
- AFFW Monthly Report, 1916 February-1917 July-August (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Incomplete set of a printed newsletter published in Paris, containing news of the AFFW, and donations desired. Issues list officers, staff, and American chapters. The June 1916 issue contains the article, "A Visit to Dr. Carrel's Hospital."
- AFFW Weekly Bulletin, 1917 November 21-1918 April 22 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Incomplete set of AFFW's Weekly Bulletin, published in Paris, and containing short articles. AFFW was working in cooperation with the American Red Cross. One article is about Gertrude Stein, a new staff member (December 8, 1917). Another short article is written by Alice B. Toklas (February 16, 1918).
- AFFW Other pamphlets and newspaper clippings (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Folder contains an AFFW pamphlet, "Somewhere in France," a plea for assistance; a single sheet, "Word from the Nancy Branch of the A.F.F.W.," on a new depot set up in Nancy, France; and two copies of a newspaper clipping "Pillows are Desired for Wounded Soldiers." Items are undated.
- AFFW Photographs (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Four photographs, 13 x 18 cm. Two show the Paris supply depot and two outdoor scenes show the motor vehicles used to deliver supplies. The vehicles have the French name of the AFFW, Comité Americain pour les Blessés Françaises, painted on the side.
- Card photographs of devastated towns and buildings (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Twenty labelled cards (and six duplicates) are 14 x 18 cm. Some have the stamp of American Fund for French Wounded on the back. On the back of others is handwritten "from Adm Pillsbury" [Rear Admiral John E. Pillsbury]. They illustrate French villages and individual buildings that were destroyed by the war.
- Postcards (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Eight postcards. Only one relates directly to AFFW, an image of the birthplace of Marechal Joffre in 1917 showing an AFFW car distributing supplies. Five cards have handwritten notes in French. Three show hospitals or hospital staff. See also postcard in Folder 1.
- War Relief Clearing House for France and her Allies, printed circulars, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Folder contains printed materials distributed in the U.S. by the War Relief Clearing House for France and her Allies. This was an American relief organization founded in 1914 and run by prominent men. It collected supplies and funds in New York for distribution in France. The documents discuss the changing relation of this organization with the American Red Cross. The relation the War Relief Clearing House and the AFFW is not clear.